Hi, everyone. My name is Janice Bria, and I'm here to introduce you guys to an organization that I'm starting up.
The organization is called the Harvard Dance Experiment, and the idea is to bring together all of the different dance groups at Harvard
and have them offer self-contained workshops for complete beginners.
So the idea is that people who really don't know how to dance but are interested in learning could try out a variety of styles that are already here at Harvard from other students
and just have a really informal space for people to get together and exercise and just have fun.
So if you think you might be interested, we're trying to gauge how many people might be interested and see if we can make this a reality.
Please join the Facebook group, Harvard Dance Experiment, or send an email to hdancexp at gmail.com. Thank you.
Hi, good morning.
So here is what we're going to do today. Today we're going to finish up with the mind-body. We're going to talk about sleep. We're going to talk about touch.
And then we're going to move on to a topic that I'm absolutely in love with, which is love.
We'll talk about relationships.
Where we finished off last time, we talked about the mind-body connection. We talked about the importance of exercise. We talked about the importance of mindfulness meditation, how it quite literally transforms,
forms, changes the form of our brain, making the left side of the prefrontal cortex more
active relative to the right side and then we talked about the importance of breathing
and how breathing, if we introduce it strategically throughout the day, can quite literally change our lives, whether it's standing in front of a red light, whether it's the first thing
when we wake up in the morning, whether it's as we enter the class or right now.
So deep breathing, deep belly breathing changes, shifts us from the fight or flight response to the relaxation response.
Remember one of the things that we talked about at the very beginning of the course is that I will not be teaching you many new things here.
And this is a clear example of that. You all know how to breathe deeply properly. you knew it from the day you were born or the moment you were born but over the
years with increasing levels of stress and the lack of recovery over the years with the mountain pressure and the speed of modern life we've had limitations
imposed on us we've been put under stress we haven't been taught how to recover and what we need to do now is chip away those limitations go back to
our innate inclination of breathing deeply and when we do that we reverse the
fight or flight and create a growth spiral between common well-being and
deep breathing that leads to more common well-being and more deep breathing. The
next topic I want to talk about but I don't want you to apply it right now
but later, is sleep. Here are some statistics about sleep. So before Edison
invented the light bulb, people slept on average about 10 hours every 24 hours. 10 hours a day, most of it at night but sometimes during the day as
well. Today the average person gets about 6.9 hours of sleep during the week
and seven and a half hours of sleep on the weekend. That's the national average.
For college students, it's a little bit different.
How many people, just so I get a show of hands, how many of you other than me get a full eight hours of sleep a night?
Okay.
I'm sure there are many more. They're probably asleep now.
So here is the national average.
Between 18 to 29-year-olds, about a quarter.
get eight hours of sleep. 75% don't get enough sleep. Now for some people, they need seven
hours, some people need nine, some 16. No. The average is eight. We all vary somewhere around it. There are very few people that need very little sleep and there are very few
people that actually need a lot of sleep. And how do we know how much sleep we need? When do we wake up naturally when we go to sleep when we're tired? And that's how we
engage it it's around eight hours now many people are saying okay for me to get eight hours of sleep I'll need 30 hour days it's not enough you know it's
it's a third of 24 hours that's too much I can't afford it well you can afford it
if you look at it as an investment if you make it a priority no it's like a business person going and making a deal and saying well I can't afford spending
$100,000 on this deal.
Well, you can't afford giving it away, but what if you will get a return on investment of 20% a year, then it changes.
Then, yeah, maybe I can afford $100,000 if there is an ROI, return on investment on it. The same with sleep. And there's a lot of return on investment on these eight hours.
A lot of research showing how important sleep is and why we need to make it a priority. So let me list just a few very briefly.
First of all, physical immune system strengthens significance.
I mean, we all know that when we go on little sleep, we end up, we're more likely to be unwell after an exam period. And, of course, it's related to stress as well.
But sleep in and of itself, enough sleep strengthens our immune system.
Energy levels. Now, there are a lot of theories going around that, well, it's better to sleep five hours than seven hours because of certain cycles. And yeah, these cycles exist.
But in general, more sleep to a point is better.
If we're sleeping more than 10 or more than 11 hours a day, sometimes it's associated with going through difficult times.
Sometimes it's associated with depression.
Depression can lead to insomnia or it can lead to the opposite, sleeping too much.
As I said, if you're sleeping 10 hours a day, it may mean that you need 10 hours a day.
It doesn't mean that you're depressed. doesn't mean that there's something there's something wrong but check it out
see throughout your life how many hours of sleep did you need on on average more
sleep is generally better up to a certain point we talked about physical
exercise and that when we don't exercise what we're doing is our weight goes up
beyond its base level, beyond its God-given or genes-given, our natural state, which is
why most diets fail when they're not associated with exercise.
The same applies to sleep. If we don't sleep enough, we go beyond our base level of weight.
Actually, correlation, and not just correlation, causation, lack of sleep to putting on weight. and if we try and diet we're fighting our nature again. Simply sleeping up
that's one of the contributing factors to effective weight management. Motor
skills. 100,000 road accidents on average each year as a result of lack
of sleep. 40,000 injuries, 1,500 people killed a year in this country as a result of lack of sleep. Either themselves being the drivers who didn't
sleep or being on the receiving end of the accident. In the workplace, day in and day
out accidents are caused because of lack of sleep, costing the economy an estimated 100
billion dollars a year. Cognitive functioning, whether it's creativity, productivity, as well
as memory that is hurt when we don't sleep, which is why sleep is such an important investment. You know, very often we say, well, let me stay up two more hours so I can study. Whereas in
In fact, you would get much more studying done, you will remember the material better, be more creative if you get these extra two hours of sleep.
Good return on investment.
Very often we can learn a lot about ourselves through babies. Why? Because babies don't suppress emotions. What happens to a baby when he or she doesn't get enough sleep?
They're cranky, they cry, they're miserable, they're anxious, I mean we know that.
Now we learn not to look like that baby that we saw when we talked about the permission to be human, to cry one moment and to laugh the next.
So we suppress these emotions, but we still have them, no different when we don't get enough sleep. That's when our fuse is shorter.
That's when we blow up more often.
That's when we feel anxious. Again, it's unhealthy on the physical level. Of course, it's unhealthy psychologically.
Affects depression in an even more significant way for two reasons. The first reason, the lack of sleep.
is likely to lead to depression is because for the physical level again just like you see a baby is cranky when it's tired we're cranky when we're tired so that's just the pure physical level of
needing sleep the second reason is a little more subtle and a little bit more interesting
what happens at night is that our mind processes a lot of the things that we have gone through
throughout the day and very often it solves unresolved issues that we've gone through through throughout the day which is why you know you go to sleep
with a math problem often you wake up in the morning with a solution but it's not just math problems that are solved at night it is also other interpersonal
intrapersonal issues that are solved throughout the night and if you look at dreams. Usually the dreams that we have early on during the night are actually
less pleasant enjoyable dreams. We're more likely to have pleasant dreams later on in the night. Why? Because the first part of the night that's when we're
working on problems, we're dealing dealing with issues. Some that were conscious, some that were not conscious during the day. Later on after
we have resolved a few of these problems, our dreams become more pleasant. Again, this
doesn't mean you can't have a nightmare at 11.30 a.m., but it means that you're more likely
to have bad dreams earlier on. And when we don't give ourselves the opportunity to quote
unquote complete our dreaming, complete problem solving through the night, we wake up with that problem unresolved and then it's there whether it's on the conscious or
subconscious level it's unresolved and we pay a price for it and over time when we have a lot of unresolved issues especially when they're suppressed or
repressed we're more likely to enter depression so sleep for the physical
need of sleep as well as for the psychological need of sleep now everyone talks about beauty sleep why because that's manifest that's obvious you can
tell when a person hasn't slept for 24, 36 hours. There are rings around the eyes so you can hide them
but still you can see when someone is enervated. But it's not just about a beauty sleep. It's also
about happiness sleep. It is also about intelligent sleep because we know that people who haven't slept
say for 24 hours, after 24 hours, their IQ is reduced by 10 points or more. So there is beauty
sleep for sure, but there is also happiness sleep as well as intelligent sleep. It's a good investment
on every level. Here are just very briefly some tips on sleep. The first thing, more or less eight
hours a day find you know what is right for you but that could mean seven hours at night and one hour in the afternoon or it could mean six and two but
generally we need eight hours a day if you can't get these eight hours a day and there are periods in your life where you won't be able to such as exam period where it may be a little bit more difficult to get the eight hours or
another stressful period or when you have children so what do you do naps naps
have actually been shown to be extremely effective. Cat naps during the day. You know, sleep for 20 minutes. It's not as good as sleeping the extra two hours at night, but it's certainly a lot better
than not getting any sleep during the day. So naps are also a very good investment. You know, take a power nap for 15-20 minutes during the day that to an extent, not like full nightly,
but to an extent, restores some of the cognitive as well as the emotional capacities.
Many people who have problems falling asleep, the reason is because they eat too late or they exercise too late and the blood is still flowing fast, the heart is still beating, they're energized.
So not to eat too much before... Some people, you know, can fall asleep as they're eating.
But there are certain people for whom it's a little bit more of an issue. So just watch your diet a little bit, watch your exercise regime, not to exercise too late.
Also, other people who have insomnia, large numbers do have insomnia, is to give yourself permission to be human.
I don't think there is one person in this room who hasn't at times had difficulty
falling asleep before the SATs, before an exam, before a date, and it's natural.
In the past, generally I don't have problems falling asleep. I get to 10 p.m. and I'm zonked.
But sometimes when I did have problems during difficult periods, stressful periods,
initially I would tell myself, okay, fall asleep now, fall asleep now, fall asleep, right? It's like, don't be anxious, don't be anxious.
And then you have pink elephants preventing you from going to sleep.
Instead, give yourself permission to be human. Now, if I have difficulty falling asleep, I say to myself, well, it's an opportunity to think and reflect.
And very often that bores me and I fall asleep.
Formation to be human.
And finally, what are your internal rhythms?
Because we have the light bulbs today,
because we're living indoors as opposed to in huts that are exposed or caves that are in touch, directly in touch with nature,
we have separated ourselves from nature. And we pay a price for it, whether we pay a price for it because we don't exercise enough, since we don't have to go hunt and gather.
And we pay a price also because we don't pay attention. We're no longer cognizant, mindful or heartful of our internal rhythms.
How many hours a night do you need?
Are you a night person or a morning person? Do you need to go to sleep at 10 p.m. or do you need to go to sleep at 5 a.m.?
what's right for you and try and create a life that is in line with your natural needs. Now that's not always possible.
If you go and work, in college it's relatively possible. You're quite flexible because you can come, this class is at 11.30 or most class, it's also videotaped.
So if you want to sleep till noon, that's fine too and then you watch it.
So you can play around with it. when you work in the future or when you were in high school and high school started at 7.30
or 8, you had to be there. But still, as much as possible, try and be aware, cognizant of your internal rhythms in terms of the hours that you need and also when you need those
hours. There's been a lot of research on sleep. There are entire seminars, classes just on
the need for sleep. Let me summarize through the work of William Demont, who is a professor at Stanford and does a lot of sleep research when he's awake.
Effects of sleep deprivation on health and well-being have been documented by research. Cognitive skills and physical performance are impaired by sleep deprivation, but mood
is affected even more.
People who get less than a full night's sleep are prone to feel less happy, more stressed,
more physically frail, and more mentally and physically exhausted as a result.
Sufficient sleep makes us feel better, happier, more vigorous, and vital.
I don't think there's one person in the room who didn't already know this.
Again, we're not teaching you anything new. I'm just reminding you of the things that you already know.
Let me move on to a topic that is related to my favorite topic, and that is touch.
Americans are, in general, again, this is a generalization, average, which in general are among the least tactile people in the world.
We spend a lot of time indulging our other senses, going to great restaurants, perfuming ourselves and our boyfriends
with the best smell that we don't touch enough.
And it's a physical need, just like sleep is, just like exercise is,
just like relationships are. And it's an important part of relationships.
The best work in the area was done by Tiffany Field who was a massage therapist and saw
the effects of massage, went out, studied this topic, got her PhD and now is a professor at the University of Miami.
And what she showed through her research and other people's research is how important getting
in touch with touch is for example for physical health whether it's our immune system strengthens
significantly with touch we can drastically without sufficient touch it helps overcome injuries
and that's not just professional massage or professional physiotherapist just the act of touch
um children grow more when they're touched and we'll talk about research in a minute some mind
boggling research. It's physical health, it's also mental health. Once again children's cognitive development is affected by touch. Mental health in
terms of mood disorders, eating disorders are associated very often with
lack of touch or not enough touch. Depression and anxiety are caused by lack
of touch can be overcome often with more touch. I hope you fully are
convinced now. Better sex life with touch. So William Johnson, sorry, William Masters
and Virginia Johnson, two of the most important sex therapists and researchers. What they have
shown is that sexual dysfunction, most sexual dysfunction, in fact between 70 and 95 percent
of them, can be solved simply with the help of touch. So what they're saying actually is that foreplay should not just be used as a means toward an end.
They're saying that it can be an end in itself.
And what touch does is essentially what positive psychology is all about.
Sex, no.
Did I say that out loud? Yes, I guess I did.
All right, so what positive psychology is about is, remember, getting us from the negative
to the zero but then getting us from the zero to the positive so what they have shown in their
research is that touch helps sexual dysfunction okay let's let's function let's get you here but
they're also saying is the touch then contributes to a thriving sexual relationship so it's not
just helping with problems, it's also making, taking us from the zero to the
thriving. Marty Seligman has a book about looking at generally psychological interventions, those that work and those that don't. And as we've talked about in
class a lot, most of the interventions do not work. We saw it with the Cambridge Somerville study, where five years of intervention actually had a negative
effect in the long term. We see it with so many of the self-help books offering quick fixes. They
don't work. He researched William Masters and Johnson's studies and what he found
during a meta-analysis is that between 70 and 95 percent of the time their prescription works. Again, this is almost unheard of in social psychology or social sciences intervention.
but these things work. Now touch is a need, as I said earlier, just like, touch is a need,
just like physical exercise is a need, just like food and sleep are a need. So there's
a story about a hospital ward for premature babies and what they found there was that
one of the sections in that hospital ward for premature babies had a much higher level of success compared to the other sections in the hospital ward.
In other words, the babies were getting better, much more promptly. They were healthier. When they followed them in the long term, they actually showed better cognitive as well as physical development.
And they were wondering about it, and they thought, I mean, could it be the air? Could it be the location in the hospital?
because everything else was identical they got the same food they got the same treatment and one of the doctors really wanted to find out what was it about
the specific section in the hospital for premature babies that actually
contributed so much to their well-being so he was you know watching the place
and then one night he was just sitting somewhere out of sight and he heard a
sound and he looked didn't want to be seen and a nurse came in a nurse whom he knew who had been in
the hospital for a long time and the nurse walked in picked up a premature baby which was against
the rules in the hospital because they cannot be touched they had to be in their incubators
picked up the baby
and just stroked him
just touched him very gently
talked to him and then put the baby down
and then walked to the next incubator picked up the baby and just very gently
stroked him and put him back down and did that to all the babies in that section of the ward now she did it late at night during her shift because it was against the rules
and then she walked out and that incident spawned off the whole line of
research about the importance of touch with babies in general specifically with premature babies so Tiffany feels that the study where premature babies were
subject to 45 minutes a day of massage while they were in the hospital very gentle massaging they're tiny and what they found was that these babies put on
47 percent more weight while they were in hospital. A year later, when they were already
at home, they had better development physically as well as in terms of cognitive skills as
well as motor skills, just as a result of being touched more often. We need touch. It
is an innate instinctual need. In fact, there's been research on touch deprivation and it wasn't
done on human beings, it was done on monkeys. Harry Harlow, a very famous psychologist worked
with a group of monkeys whom he took away from their mothers, didn't provide them any touch.
every other need was provided. And what he found was that these monkeys didn't grow physically as much as the other monkeys.
Their cognitive development was impaired and they displayed autistic-like behavior. For example, they would sit down, put their legs up and then rock.
Have you seen this? Like in the movie with Dustin Hoffman, The Rain Man, where he would
just sit down and rock this way. So many of these monkeys displayed exactly this behavior,
this rocking autistic behavior. Cruel study, whether it's done on ants or monkeys, certainly
on human beings. Unfortunately, it has been done on human beings. This is one of the largest natural tragic experiments ever carried out. This specifically was done in
Romania under Ceaușescu, the cruel dictator that ruled over the country
until 1989. One thing that he did was take many kids away from their parents especially if the parents were dissidents, especially if the parents were
not quote-unquote kosher communists. So he took their kids and raised 150,000
kids in homes away from their parents. Now these homes, because it was a very
poor country, had no money for nurses, for enough nurses, had no money for
enough support staff in general. So while these kids got all their physical needs
in terms of food, water, and they were cleaned, they did not get much affection. Not because the nurses didn't want to give them affection, they just
didn't have the time. In 1989, after the wall fell, Ceausescu was ousted, and these kids
were released from these homes, and psychologists went in, and what they saw was the result
of this tragic natural experiment. In terms of physical growth, these kids were between
3 and 10% in size relative to their age group. Cognitive growth, the level of way below the 100
IQ average. Motor development also impaired significantly as a result of lack of touch and
many of these kids were sitting down with their legs to their chest and just rocking.
the effect of touch deprivation now touch is important once again to get us here
and we're here, we're fine the question is how do we get beyond this well touch can take us there as well not just to being okay but also to thriving
the importance of touch Virginia Satir who's a psychologist
has this to say
We need four hugs a day for survival.
We need eight hugs a day for maintenance.
We need 12 hugs a day for growth.
Again, she says that half, you know, in jest, there is not actual research showing how many hugs. Very good. You have 11 more left for today.
But good, good.
So there is, though, actual research on hugs. So this is Jane Klippman.
who did research, and here was the intervention, very simple.
It was, every day, give at least five hugs.
These are frontal hugs, not with your partner, just hugs to different people.
Friends can be your partner as well, but these are specifically non-sexual hugs.
And what she found after four weeks was that the people who were in this group, as opposed to the control group, and the control group had to write how many hours a day they read,
the control group level of happiness obviously didn't go up. The group that hugged five times a day went up significantly.
Now, this experiment, when she talks about it, she says it was much more difficult for some people, especially for men.
But even the men who were part of it, most of them hugged, so they would do it on the sports field. that would find opportunities or somehow got in five hugs a day.
And those people who did that actually became happier.
Now, I was going to assign this as your response paper this week.
I'm not going to do it, but I recommend it. So it's a very strong recommendation and suggestion.
From now on and for the rest of your life, at least five hugs, preferably 12.
The nice thing about hugs is that it's a win-win because when we hug someone, we're hugged back. When we touch someone, we're touched back. It's like happiness.
When we share it, it grows.
It's a win-win, positive thumb game.
The important thing to keep in mind about hugs and touch in general is to respect the other person
because not everyone feels as comfortable being touched as we do. Or we may not feel comfortable being touched, and that's fine.
for many reasons. You know, one could be upbringing, one could be just physically people are different or some people who enjoy touch much more than others and that's fine, it's natural.
So we need to respect other people's boundaries as well as have others respect our own.
But in general, touch is important, touch is good and we need to become a more tactile individual as well as a more tactile society.
Let me show you an example now of how some people like hugs more than others.
Okay, so once again, here is the prescription.
Very simple.
Four times at least a week of 30 minutes of physical exercise, at least.
Mindfulness meditation, if it's good for you, every day, 10, 15 minutes.
If not, at the very least, a few deep breaths strategically placed throughout the day.
Eight hours of sleep a night and at least five, ideally 12, hugs a day.
This is probably the most powerful psychological prescription that you will ever get or hear about.
and all it does is bring us back to our base level of well-being, our God-given or genes-given level of happiness.
Let's move on now to another topic.
Here is what I want to talk to you about today.
Okay, so let's talk about love.
The most talked about topic, the most felt topic,
talked about everywhere from the dining room to the bedroom to the classroom
evidently and yet it's the most misunderstood topic out there
relationships close intimate relationships whether it's with lovers whether it was family members whether it was close soulmates friends is the
number one predictor of happiness our focus today will be on and the next
lesson will be on romantic relationships however we're focusing on romantic relationships simply because in many ways it's the tip of the stem it includes
many of the things that other relationships include but the ideas that we talk about apply as much to close friendships family relationships as well
Let me begin by showing you a nice little excerpt from the movie In Her Shoes, where
Cameron Diaz reads something, a beautiful poem, to her sister in the movie, who's getting married.
And now, a very special moment, young lady.
uh this isn't in the program because it's a surprise a surprise rose a lot uh usually she
hates it i think well i hope she likes this it's a poem by you i carry your heart with me
i carry it in my heart i am never without it anywhere i go you go my dear and whatever
is done by only me, is your doing, my darling. I fear no fate, for you are my fate, my human.
I want no world. So beautiful, you are my world, my truth. Here is the deeper secret
in my mouth. Here is the root of the root, and the bud of the bud, and the sky of the
What is that? Roots of the roots, bud of the bud, the thing that keeps the stars apart.
Well, let's try and understand it just a little bit more than we already do.
Once again, relationships are a natural need. No person is an island. No one can survive.
No one can certainly thrive without relationships.
Let's revisit the research that we talked about a couple of months ago of extremely happy people.
Remember Ed Diener and Marty Seligman chose the 10% happiest group, the tip of the stem, and studied them.
And one of the things that they found, if you remember, was that they experienced hardships just like everyone else. They experience anxiety, stress, depression at times, frustration.
However, the difference between them and the rest,
those who are not at the tip of the stem, is that they recover more promptly. They have a stronger immune system, in other words.
And one of the reasons why they have a stronger immune system, one of the reasons why they interpret their experiences differently
is because they have, and this is a differentiator between them and the rest,
They have thriving interpersonal relationships, whether it's with romantic partners or with soulmates or with family members or all of the above.
But this is one distinguishing characteristic of this group, that they have close, intimate relationships, and that makes all the difference.
why for two reasons first of all because when you're happy and you share your happiness with someone close to you who truly cares about that enhances amplifies your happiness as well as
their happiness that's the win-win when you go through hardships and difficulties
having close relationships helps us to overcome it so again whether it's from the negative to the zero or from the zero to the positive. Close intimate relationships contribute
significantly to becoming happy. The key though in relationships is to know yourself, meaning to know your needs, because we don't all have the same
relationship need. There is no one prescription. No, there is no, okay, five hugs a day and you'll be happier. Five close friends, you know, one or two
lovers and there is no such prescription. It's different for different people. And I
want to revisit the lasagna principle. Remember the lasagna principle from the happiness book
and that is that we all need, the example I gave there is, so I love my family is the
most important thing in the world to me. However, that doesn't mean I want to spend eight or
10 hours a day with my family every day, all day. I also need my quota of solitude, I need my yoga,
I need my exercise, my writing, my teaching. That does not mean that my family is any less
important to me. Or let's say I love to write, which I do. I can write for three hours a day, not longer. And the reason why it was the lasagna principle, if you remember, lasagna is my favorite
food and whenever I go home my mom makes lasagna but that does not mean I want lasagna every day all day you know five times a week is more than enough for me
or once a week but you need to find your quota the same with relationships the same with relationships ask yourself how many hours a day is it good for me
pleasant for me enjoyable for me to spend with other people one of the
things that differentiates people in terms of the right amount is introversion and extroversion.
We actually have a physiological base level of where we are compared to the optimum. Let me
illustrate. So there is what's called an optimal level of arousal, cognitively speaking, optimum
level of arousal and this let's say is our optimum level of arousal and we're
all born somewhere around us either above below very few people are right on the
line introverts have a higher level of arousal higher innate level of arousal
This is the introversion.
Extroverts have a lower level of arousal compared to the optimal level.
Now we all physically see or emotionally, cognitively, and physically look for experiencing the optimal level of arousal because that's where it's most convenient.
That's when we are at our best, that's when we enjoy ourselves more.
Which is why introverts, whose innate natural state is above the optimal level of arousal, actually need to reduce level of arousal.
So they enjoy spending time by themselves.
In contrast, extroverts have a lower arousal level.
And it's not as pleasant as when they get it to the optimum level. so they go out to a party where there is a lot of arousal, a lot of things happening, a lot of people,
in order to get to their optimal level of arousal. Which is why generally, what does alcohol do?
Alcohol reduces our level of arousal.
Which is why introverts very often need a glass of wine or a bottle before they dance.
Because to dance when other people are watching increases levels of arousal. So what the alcohol does is reduce their level of arousal, and then dancing is comfortable, and they're fine with it.
In contrast, many extroverts need coffee, which is a stimulant, in order to stay awake,
because the coffee gets them up to their optimal level of arousal.
Again, I'm giving you a sketch of this line of research ever since I think for decades about introversion and extroversion.
Now, by the way, this does not mean that we cannot act, in the words of Brian Little,
we cannot act out of nature, meaning an introvert can act like an extrovert.
Here I am, I'm an introvert, and by the way, we were born with this state, it's innate.
So I was born an introvert, and yet when I stand in front of the class and sing beautiful songs, I'm acting like an extrovert.
However, the important thing while we can act out of nature is to understand that very often this enervates us.
It takes away energy, it's difficult for us because we're acting, so if I'm here,
when I teach I go even higher, even further from my optimal level of arousal and that takes away energy, which is why introverts, after acting like extroverts, whether it's
at a party or in a lecture, need what Brian Little calls a restorative niche, a restorative niche, a place to restore.
And that would be a place where they would spend time one-on-one with someone or some hours of solitude of recovery.
Remember, the problem is not stress.
The problem is not stress. The problem is when we don't have recovery.
And introverts need recovery, some time on their own, some time one-on-one. That's why for me, for example, a form of recovery is office hours.
It's easy for me to meet students for four hours straight.
It's a form of recovery.
If I was only teaching and only standing in front of an audience, that would ultimately lead to overwork and to me being lethargic.
Same with an extrovert. If you're an extrovert, sometimes you have to do introvert stuff.
So, for example, you need to study for an exam.
And yes, it would be nice to study for an exam at the Kong, but maybe not that helpful. So you study by yourself or with one person.
And then what do you need after that as a restorative niche? Because it's enervating for an extrovert to be far from their optimal level of arousal. You need a restorative niche. Where is that restorative niche?
I need to go out and party with friends.
And that for them is a restorative niche.
So again, know thyself. Know what your relationship needs are.
Doesn't mean you cannot act out of nature. You can.
But at the same time, you must be able to have a form of recovery, a restorative niche, according to your first nature, be it an introvert or an extrovert. To summarize,
the number of relationships that you need
That would be best for you depends on your personal unique needs.
The number of hours you want to spend with other people differs for everyone. There is no right or wrong here. Some people enjoy spending time 10 hours a day with friends, you know, more of the extroverts.
Other people, you know, one-on-one, intimate time, two, three hours a day is what they need.
There's no right or wrong here. It doesn't mean you love people any less. or neither does it mean that you don't need intimate relationships if you're one or the other.
Both need close, intimate relationships.
Soulmates, romantic partners, family members, whatever it is, it's a need.
David Myers, there are few stronger predictors of happiness than a close, nurturing, equitable, intimate, lifelong companionship with one's best friend.
There's been a lot more research done on opposite-sex relationship than on same-sex relationship.
However, over the last few years, especially through the work of John Gottman from University of Washington,
probably the leading researcher in this area, he's been doing much more work on single-sex relationship.
And what they're finding, some very similar results with some differences. And we'll get to some of those interesting because they're informing differences.
Probably not today, but next time. So when I talk about the relationship I'm talking about now, the relationship that David Myers is talking about is companionship, romantic relationship that is lifelong.
Same sex or opposite sex.
The interesting thing about relationships is that everyone benefits from it. But as I've mentioned already once before, men benefit more.
Why do they benefit more? Because for the first time, often, men have someone they can share with,
whereas women have more often, more likely,
have their girlfriends whom they talk to about certain issues they share their happiness as well as their sorrows with.
However, both sexes in opposite and same-sex relationships benefit from intimate relationships.
Let me show you a quick video excerpt of a description
of what marriage is all about you wake up in the morning and she's there you you
you come home at night and she's there you eat she's there you go to sleep
there and I know that sounds like a bad thing but it's not it's not not if it's
If it's the right person, then it's good. It's good. It's really, really good.
I would like a minute for rebuttal.
So let's look at relationships. First of all, let's look at the state of affairs.
At what's actually going on with relationships, long-term relationships today, marriage or other.
What we see is not a very pretty picture. So when it comes to marriages, two-thirds of marriages today end up in divorce.
This does not mean that the other third are thriving because very often, very often, people
stay together out of a sense of duty, out of habit, because of a lack of alternative,
because they think this is their lasting life.
now
and I'm certainly not going to argue for the fact that
there are no marriages or relationships that should be dissolved of course there should be not every relationship is right and we often make mistakes but the argument I am going to make
is that many of the relationships that end or many of the relationships that reach a state in the words of Thoreau of quiet desperation
of just being there of just sort of an inertia many of these relationships either should not have ended or can actually thrive.
The problem, though, is that we see,
certainly with the two-thirds you end up in divorce, but also with the other third, very often there is a failure to sustain love over time.
I don't know anyone who has gone to the wedding ceremony
or exchanged vows in another setting. I don't know of any couple who did that and say, well, this is just temporary. We're only going to do it for two years
until death do us part, but not really.
You know, when people go into a relationship, their thought, their hope
is to continue the exact same love and passion that they have at the beginning of the relationship.
This is how relationships start. This is the promise of love.
And yet, more often than not, evidently, things don't turn out as we expected them to have turned out.
One of the main reasons for it and one of the reasons that is cited by numerous sex therapists or psychologists,
and again you don't need research for that because it's so self-evident,
one of the reasons is because love and especially lust and passion wears over time.
Because we know that novelty produces higher levels of arousal or in the words of Daryl Bem,
from Cornell University psychologist, the exotic is the erotic. If it's new, it's more interesting,
more fascinating. And this explains why so many relationships end. The question though is,
is that necessarily part of our nature? And the answer is yes and no. Yes, it's necessarily part
of our nature that novelty excites us more. That we adapt to what happens. Remember, we're change
detectors. We become much more aroused whether it's cognitively, psychologically or physically,
physiologically when there is something new. And we adapt over time for good and ill.
Now it would be wonderful if that wasn't the case for positive events, for positive experiences such
as finding a romantic partner but it is and the question is what do we do with it let me first
share with you before we get to what do we do with it let me share with you a study that i ran hopefully it will be published in a respectable academic journal soon but my research question
this is a very important one was who's the hottest woman and the hottest man in the world
or scientifically put, who's the fairest of them all? And I posed this question to my sophomore class
when I taught a sophomore tutorial in psychology.
And we had a long debate about it, but at the end we came up with scientific results. So those of you who don't have the PowerPoints in front of you, who do you think was chosen as the hottest male?
You get an A.
Anyone else wants an A? Who was chosen as the hottest male in the world? Bill Clinton? No.
Who? George Clooney? Close but no cigar. You got it.
Here he is standing right outside Troy telling Helen that he'll be right over.
Who is the hottest female in the world, as scientifically proven by the sophomore tutorial?
You, right.
Another ace.
Who was she?
Angelina Jolino?
Halle Berry.
Here she is telling Adrian Brody that she'll kill him if he comes a step closer to her.
Now, imagine this. Imagine this.
Imagine that you find your Brad Pitt or Halle Berry, your ideal man or woman.
Not only are they sizzling hot, but they're also extremely sensitive, wise, way beyond their years,
saintly, generous benevolent, make 10 million dollars a movie and most importantly
they love you just as much if not more than you love them just imagine if that happens and you meet your Brad Pitt
or whoever your Achilles heel is or you meet Halle Berry or Superwoman or Spiderwoman or whomever it is
for you imagine that and you see them and you talk to them and you fall in love and they fall
in love with you and you get married and the first night after your marriage or before that that's
your choice you get home no armor is going to stop you no gun is going to drive you away you make
compassionate love for hours and days and weeks and months you don't even turn
up for positive psychology it's so good imagine that just imagine and then of
course screen comes down and you live happily and lustily ever after right
maybe now imagine this five years into the relationship with this amazing
amazing sensitive wise hot wealthy person five years into the relationship you
take part in a psychological experiment and here is the experiment they hook you up to all these electrodes to all these met physiological kinds of measurements
and they measure your level of physiological arousal.
And then your Brad Pitt or Halle Berry or whomever it is walk into the room and they see how physically aroused you become.
And then they leave and then someone else who is moderately attractive, you know, no Brad Pitt, Halle Berry, but someone who is moderately attractive walks into the room.
When would you become more physically?
Instinctually, when would you become more physically aroused? In general, it doesn't always happen, but overwhelming majority of times.
You've become more physically aroused when the new person comes in.
Why? Because the exotic is erotic, because novelty excites.
Now, we laugh about this, but it actually to some extent explains the statistics,
which is why so many relationships go sour when they start off with the best
of intentions with the most honest intentions and yet they flounder and this
is part of the reason why so is this bad news not necessarily well it's not bad
or good it is it's like talking about the law of gravity the law of gravity bad No, it's not bad. Is it good? It's not good either. It simply is.
It's like what we talked about, painful emotions. Are they bad? No. Are they good? No. They simply are.
And if we want to lead a happy life, if we want to have a thriving, healthy relationship,
what we need to do is first and foremost accept nature.
It's not good or bad news, it's simply real news. or not news because again we all know this and the question is what do we do
with it how do we obey nature so that we can command it and what I'm going to talk about today and even more so next time is how we can take relationships
given the fact that novelty excites given the fact that on the physiological level the arousal will be higher by the way it applies for men and women the
excitement will be higher when there's a new person. Given all that, how can we create
relationships that thrive, that soar, that go way beyond the zero to the positive? And
it's possible, and positive psychology can help us do it. The first step before accepting
reality is understanding what true love really means. Because many people, many people ask
this question, does it even exist in reality? It exists in fiction, it exists in movies,
but these characters on the movie screen are literally larger than life. They deliver
perfect lines. They make perfect love. How am I going to be able to do that? And therefore,
how am I going to be able to experience what they're experiencing? Does true love really
exist because can I ever live up to the kind of relationship that Ingrid Bergman and Humphrey
Bogart had? Can I reach the height of 40,000 feet? Can I have the same mystical connection
as Meg Ryan and Tom Hanks had? And will I ever be able to sleep with the British Prime
minister or issue grant is it possible is it real and you know self-help books
don't help much one of my actual favorite self-help writers Leo Buscalia
was also a professor at University of Southern California wonderful writer
compassionate passionate speaker helped me a lot with the first self-help book that I read. It was about living, loving, and learning. Here is what he writes about
love and relationships. Perfect love is rare indeed, for to be a lover will require that
you continually have the subtlety of the very wise, the flexibility of the child, the sensitivity
of the artist, the understanding of the philosopher, the acceptance of the saint, the tolerance
of the scholar and the fortitude of the certain. What a beautiful passage. So beautiful and
so detrimental. Who can live up to this? Anyone? You see, there is no perfect love. To expect
this of myself, of my partner, of our relationship is to set us up for failure. I would not
want Tommy to expect this in her partner. Because I can guarantee you I will fail her,
I have failed her according to the standards. As she me. It's impossible, it's unrealistic
and we set ourselves up for failure when our expectations are larger than life, when our
expectations are perfect lines or perfect love. And yet this is what we read about, this is
what we see and we begin to internalize this, the straight line of a relationship which is perfect
and unreal. But while perfect love doesn't exist, true love does. True love exists between imperfect
humans. What is true love? How can positive psychology help us identify it? First, by asking
different questions and have been mostly been asked in this area. Second, by focusing not just
on what works but on what works best. On the few relationships that really thrive, that have not
dissolved, that have not ended, that are not just here in a state of quiet desperation or as Pink
Floyd said, just comfortably numb. But relationships that are here, let's learn from them. Let's learn from the tip of the stem. So the first thing we need to do is reframe the questions.
Remember we did the exact same thing with at-risk youth. We did the exact same thing with people
who are happy, healthy and successful. We did the same thing when it came to the geometric
shapes. Because questions start a quest and questions define reality. And traditional
psychology has asked couples, counselors, researchers in the area asked, why do so many
long-term relationships fail? Why do so many people after a year or two or five years together
end their relationship? Why is it that many people who do stay together are no longer
thriving. And one of the answers that they got was because novelty arouses,
because it's part of human nature to seek excitement. The erotic is exotic.
That's one of the answers. And again it's a true answer, it's an important thing to take into consideration. It's part of reality whether we like it or not. But that question is not enough. Just like the similar question was not enough when
we asked about at-risk population or when I asked you about the geometric shape and when we only ask this question, we quite literally miss a part of reality and a very important
part of reality, a part of reality that can lead to lasting, thriving, passionate relationships.
And the question that positive psychology asks is what makes some relationships thrive and grow stronger over time?
because there are such relationships.
I was fortunate to see a relationship like that between my grandmother whom I told you about and my grandfather.
They were married for 53 years.
The pictures that we have of them and the way they were together is that my grandmother who was the matriarch of the family and a very powerful woman but always also very humorous
was of her sitting down in my grandfather next to her with his hand on her shoulder
just looking at her, just like a 16 year old in love. They were married for 53 years.
Of course with their ups and downs and disagreements and disappointments, they're not perfect either.
But they had a thriving relationship, passionate relationship.
What is it about these relationships? What makes them successful?
And the important question is what can we learn and apply to our relationships?
if what we're interested in is a long-term passionate relationship.
So let's learn from what works. Let's learn not just from what works, but let's learn from what works best.
The best relationships that we can look at and study and learn from. Here are some of the lessons that we can learn from these relationships.
and I'm going to draw on two researchers. First, John Gottman, whom I mentioned before,
and the second, David Schnark. David Schnark, as well as John Gottman, as I mentioned earlier, have done research, very good research, on opposite as well as same-sex relationships.
Here are some of the things that they find I will talk about. First, when I figured out how to predict divorce, I thought I had found the key to saving marriages. But like so many
experts before me I was wrong. I was not able to crack the code of saving
marriages until I started to analyze what went right in happy marriages. He
wrote this in 1999. In 2001 he took it a step further and we'll see next week in
the research where he studied same-sex relationships and learned even more things than he had learned when studying what goes well in opposite sex relationships but the
key was to study successful relationship whatever the relationship was whatever its nature was
and when he studied those that made all the difference he could predict he can predict divorce with an accuracy level of 94 percent 94 percent that's an unheard of figure in social
sciences. Quite remarkable. And then he was able to do it, but it didn't help him create
better long-term relationships. It was only when he started to ask this question, what
makes some relationships thrive and grow stronger over time, that's when he went ahead and was
able to prescribe better relationships. The second person we're drawn is David Schnark. And here is what he says in his wonderful book, Passionate Marriage.
Cellulite and sexual potential are highly correlated.
What he showed in his research studying the best relationship is that not only do they enjoy spending time together over the years,
but that the best sex that they have in their lives doesn't come when they are 18 or 25 or 35.
five it actually is for 50s and 60 year olds so you have a lot to look forward
to now that does not mean that does not mean it can't be great at 18 it can be
even greater at 50 and 60 that's what he showed in his research of thriving relationships now these are not the majority of the relationships
unfortunately because most people today by the age 50 and 60 they're into their
second or third marriage or long-term relationship however very often it is
later on that it becomes better and that's where it veers away goes away from the just physiological level of arousal which may be stronger at the age
of you know 24 they say for men and 35 for women I mean I don't know where they get these numbers from, but we actually peak potentially, note the word here, potentially
we peak in our 50s and 60s. Why? We'll understand later. So here are the things that we're going
to talk about in the next class. We're going to engage in growing tip statistic. We're going to look at the best relationships, just like we looked at the best teacher, Marva
Collins, just like we looked at the best meditators, Lama Oster and others. We're going to look at the best relationships and ask what can we learn from it and apply
to our lives. One minute, one minute. And we're going to talk about four
different topics. First, that a relationship is about hard work. If you want to thrive at work, you need to work hard. If you want to thrive in a
relationship, you need to invest. Second, and we'll talk about how to invest, but The best relationships are ones that create high levels of intimacy,
that get to know one another in a deeper level, and these are the relationships that thrive. These are the relationships that also maintain passion
and enhance passion five, 10, and 50 years hence.
The best relationships are not relationships devoid of conflict, and we'll talk about what that means and what that looks like.
And finally, we're in a positive psychology class. It is about appreciating the positive, because when we appreciate the good, the good appreciates, whether in ourselves or in others.
See you on Thursday.